<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Maininformation xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
 
  <Intro>
   <Information>
    <Id>0</Id>
    <heading>Human Right</heading>
    <text>
	
	What is human right?

	Human Rights refers to the concept of human beings as having universal natural rights, or status, regardless of legal jurisdiction or other 
	localizing, such as ethnicity, sex and nationality,.</text>
	 </Information>
  </Intro>
  <Intro>
   <Information>
    <Id>1</Id>
    <heading>INTRODUCTION</heading>
    <text>
	
	Even though the origin of human rights is ancient, the international concern with human rights may be said to be of comparatively recent 
	origin. The UN Charter marks the advent of systematic human rights protection within the International system.

	The idea of human rights is as old as humanity, its systematic proclamation and declaration are more recent. The world’s first bill of human 
	rights was discovered on a clay tablet dating back from the reign of Cyrus the Great (555- 529 BC).

	The documents which form the historical foundation of modern human rights jurisprudence are the English Bill of Rights (1688), the 
	American Declaration of Independence (1776) and the French Declaration of Rights of Man (1789).
	
	The legal process in the universality of human rights effectively commenced with the Universal Declaration of Human Rights 1948 (UDHR).</text>
    </Information>
  </Intro>
  <Intro>
   <Information>
    <Id>2</Id>
    <heading>MEANING OF HUMAN RIGHTS:</heading>
    <text>
	
	Human Beings are rational beings. They by virtue of their being human possess certain basic and inalienable rights which are commonly 
	known as human rights.

	Human Rights are defined as all those rights which are essential for the protection and maintenance of dignity of individuals and create 
	conditions in which every human being can develop his personality to the fullest extent may be termed as human rights.

	Human rights become operative with the birth of an individual. Human rights, being the birth right, are inherent in all the individuals 
	irrespective of their caste, religion, sex and nationality.

	Because of their immense significance to human beings ; human rights are also sometimes referred to as fundamental rights, basic rights, 
	inherent rights, natural rights and birth rights.</text>
	 </Information>
  </Intro>
 
  
  
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>3</Id>
      <heading>
	                                                         The Universal Declaration of Human Rights	  </heading>
      <text>
	  
	  
Whereas recognition of the inherent dignity and of the equal and inalienable rights of all members of the human family is the foundation of freedom
, justice and peace in the world,
Whereas it is essential to promote the development of friendly relations between nations,
Whereas a common understanding of these rights and freedoms is of the greatest importance for the full realization of this pledge,

Now, therefore,	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>4</Id>
      <heading>The General Assembly</heading>
      <text>
	  
Proclaims this Universal Declaration of Human Rights as a common standard of achievement for all peoples and all nations, to the end that every 
individual and every organ of society, keeping this Declaration constantly in mind, shall strive by teaching and education to promote respect for 
these rights and freedoms and by progressive measures, national and international, to secure their universal and effective recognition and 
observance, both among the peoples of Member States themselves and among the peoples of territories under their jurisdiction.
On December 10, 1948, the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR)was adopted by the 56 members of the United Nations. The vote was 
unanimous, although eight nations chose to abstain.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>5</Id>
      <heading>Article 1</heading>
      <text>
All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and conscience and should act towards one another 
in a spirit of brotherhood.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>6</Id>
      <heading>Article 2</heading>
      <text>
Everyone is entitled to all the rights and freedoms set forth in this Declaration, without distinction of any kind, such as race, colour, sex, language, 
religion, political or other opinion, national or social origin, property, birth or other status.
Furthermore, no distinction shall be made on the basis of the political, jurisdictional or international status of the country or territory to which a 
person belongs, whether it be independent, trust, non‐self‐governing or under any other limitation of sovereignty.</text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>7</Id>
      <heading>Article 3</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to life, liberty and the security of person.</text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>8</Id>
      <heading>Article 4</heading>
      <text>
No one shall be held in slavery or servitude; slavery and the slave trade shall be prohibited in all their forms.</text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>9</Id>
      <heading>Article 5</heading>
      <text>
No one shall be subjected to torture or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>10</Id>
      <heading>Article 6</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to recognition everywhere as a person before the law.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>11</Id>
      <heading>Article 7</heading>
      <text>
All are equal before the law and are entitled without any discrimination to equal protection of the law. All are entitled to equal protection against 
any discrimination in violation of this Declaration and against any incitement to such discrimination.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>12</Id>
      <heading>Article 8</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to an effective remedy by the competent national tribunals for acts violating the fundamental rights granted him by the 
constitution or by law.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>13</Id>
      <heading>Article 9</heading>
      <text>
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary arrest, detention or exile.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>14</Id>
      <heading>Article 10</heading>
      <text>
Everyone is entitled in full equality to a fair and public hearing by an independent and impartial tribunal, in the determination of his rights and 
obligations and of any criminal charge against him.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>15</Id>
      <heading>Article 11</heading>
      <text>
Everyone charged with a penal offence has the right to be presumed innocent until proved guilty according to law in a public trial at which he has 
had all the guarantees necessary for his defence.
No one shall be held guilty of any penal offence on account of any act or omission which did not constitute a penal offence, under national or 
international law, at the time when it was committed. Nor shall a heavier penalty be imposed than the one that was applicable at the time the 
penal offence was committed.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>16</Id>
      <heading>Article 12</heading>
      <text>
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary interference with his privacy, family, home or correspondence, nor to attacks upon his honour and reputation. 
Everyone has the right to the protection of the law against such interference or attacks.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>17</Id>
      <heading>Article 13</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to freedom of movement and residence within the borders of each State.
Everyone has the right to leave any country, including his own, and to return to his country.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>18</Id>
      <heading>Article 14</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to seek and to enjoy in other countries asylum from persecution.
This right may not be invoked in the case of prosecutions genuinely arising from non political crimes or from acts contrary to the purposes and
principles of the United Nations.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>19</Id>
      <heading>Article 15</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to a nationality.
No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his nationality nor denied the right to change his nationality.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>20</Id>
      <heading>Article 16</heading>
      <text>
Men and women of full age, without any limitation due to race, nationality or religion, have the right to marry and to found a family. They are entitled 
to equal rights as to marriage, during marriage and at its dissolution.
Marriage shall be entered into only with the free and full consent of the intending spouses.
The family is the natural and fundamental group unit of society and is entitled to protection by society and the State.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>21</Id>
      <heading>Article 17</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to own property alone as well as in association with others.
No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his property.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>22</Id>
      <heading>Article 18</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion; this right includes freedom to change his religion or belief, and freedom, 
either alone or in community with others and in public or private, to manifest his religion or belief in teaching, practice, worship and 
observance.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>23</Id>
      <heading>Article 19</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to freedom of opinion and expression; this right includes freedom to hold opinions without interference and to seek, receive 
and impart information and ideas through any media and regardless of frontiers.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>24</Id>
      <heading>Article 20</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to freedom of peaceful assembly and association.
No one may be compelled to belong to an association.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>25</Id>
      <heading>Article 21</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to take part in the government of his country, directly or through freely chosen representatives.
Everyone has the right of equal access to public service in his country.
The will of the people shall be the basis of the authority of government; this will shall be expressed in periodic and genuine elections which shall be 
by universal and equal suffrage and shall be held by secret vote or by equivalent free voting procedures.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>26</Id>
      <heading>Article 22</heading>
      <text>
Everyone, as a member of society, has the right to social security and is entitled to realization, through national effort and international co‐operation 
and in accordance with the organization and resources of each State, of the economic, social and cultural rights indispensable for his dignity and the 
free development of his personality.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>27</Id>
      <heading>Article 23</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to work, to free choice of employment, to just and favourable conditions of work and to protection against unemployment.
Everyone, without any discrimination, has the right to equal pay for equal work.
Everyone who works has the right to just and favourable remuneration ensuring for himself and his family an existence worthy of human dignity, 
and supplemented, if necessary, by other means of social protection.
Everyone has the right to form and to join trade unions for the protection of his interests.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>28</Id>
      <heading>Article 24</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to rest and leisure, including reasonable limitation of working hours and periodic holidays with pay.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>29</Id>
      <heading>Article 25</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate for the health and well‐being of himself and of his family, including food, clothing, housing 
and medical care and necessary social services, and the right to security in the event of unemployment, sickness, disability, widowhood, old age or 
other lack of livelihood in circumstances beyond his control.
Motherhood and childhood are entitled to special care and assistance. All children, whether born in or out of wedlock, shall enjoy the same social 
protection.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>30</Id>
      <heading>Article 26</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be free, at least in the elementary and fundamental stages. Elementary education shall be 
compulsory. Technical and professional education shall be made generally available and higher education shall be equally accessible to all on 
the basis of merit.
Education shall be directed to the full development of the human personality and to the strengthening of respect for human rights and fundamental 
freedoms. It shall promote understanding, tolerance and friendship among all nations, racial or religious groups, and shall further the activities 
of the United Nations for the maintenance of peace.
Parents have a prior right to choose the kind of education that shall be given to their children.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>31</Id>
      <heading>Article 27</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has the right freely to participate in the cultural life of the community, to enjoy the arts and to share in scientific advancement and its 
benefits.
Everyone has the right to the protection of the moral and material interests resulting from any scientific, literary or artistic production of which he is 
the author.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>32</Id>
      <heading>Article 28</heading>
      <text>
Everyone is entitled to a social and international order in which the rights and freedoms set forth in this Declaration can be fully realized.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>33</Id>
      <heading>Article 29</heading>
      <text>
Everyone has duties to the community in which alone the free and full development of his personality is possible.
In the exercise of his rights and freedoms, everyone shall be subject only to such limitations as are determined by law solely for the purpose of 
securing due recognition and respect for the rights and freedoms of others and of meeting the just requirements of morality, public order and the 
general welfare in a democratic society.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  <UniversalDeclaration>
    <Information>
      <Id>34</Id>
      <heading>Article 30</heading>
      <text>
Nothing in this Declaration may be interpreted as implying for any State, group or person any right to engage in any activity or to perform any act 
aimed at the destruction of any of the rights and freedoms set forth herein.
	  </text>
    </Information>
  </UniversalDeclaration>
  
  <Htypes>
    <Information>
      <Id>35</Id>
      <heading>Types of Human Rights
1. Individual (civil) rights</heading>
      <text>Life, liberty, and security of the person; privacy and freedom of movement; ownership of property; freedom of thought, conscience, and religious belief and practice; prohibition of slavery, torture, and cruel or degrading punishment.</text>
    </Information>
  </Htypes>
  <Htypes>
    <Information>
      <Id>36</Id>
      <heading>2. Rule of law
</heading>
      <text>Equal recognition before the law and equal protection of the law; effective legal remedy for violation of rights; impartial hearing and trial; presumption of innocence; and prohibition of arbitrary arrest.</text>
    </Information>
  </Htypes>
  <Htypes>
    <Information>
      <Id>37</Id>
      <heading>3. Rights of political expression
</heading>
      <text>Freedom of expression, assembly, and association; the right to take part in government; and periodic and meaningful elections with universal and equal suffrage.</text>
    </Information>
  </Htypes>
  <Htypes>
    <Information>
      <Id>38</Id>
      <heading>4. Economic and social rights
</heading>
      <text>An adequate standard of living; free choice of employment; protection against unemployment; "just and favorable remuneration"; the right to form and join trade unions; "reasonable limitation of working hours"; free elementary education; social security; and the "highest attainable standard of physical and mental health."</text>
    </Information>
  </Htypes>
  <Htypes>
    <Information>
      <Id>39</Id>
      <heading>5. Rights of communities
</heading>
      <text>Self-determination and protection of minority cultures.</text>
    </Information>
  </Htypes>
  <Types>
    <Information>
      <Id>40</Id>
      <heading>KINDS OF HUMAN RIGHTS</heading>
      <text>There are two kinds of human rights :</text>
    </Information>
  </Types>
  <Types>
    <Information>
      <Id>41</Id>
      <heading>1. Civil and political rights.
2. Economic social and cultural rights.</heading>
      
    </Information>
  </Types>
  <Types>
    <Information>
      <Id>42</Id>
      <heading>1. Civil and political rights.</heading>
      <text>Civil rights and liberties are referred to those rights which are related to the protection of the right to life and personal liberty. They are essential for 
a person so that he may live a dignified life. Such rights include right to life, liberty, right to privacy, freedom from torture and right to own property.
These rights also known as (freedom from).

Whereas political rights may be referred to those rights which allow a person to participate in the government of a state. For e.g. right to vote, right 
to be elected and right to take part in conduct of public affairs.

The nature of both civil and political rights may be different but they are inter-related and therefore it does not appear logical to differentiate them.
This reason led to the formulation of one covenant covering both civil and political rights into one covenant i.e. International Covenant on civil and
political rights.</text>
    </Information>
  </Types>
  <Types>
    <Information>
      <Id>43</Id>
      <heading>2. Economic, social and cultural rights:</heading>
      <text>Economic, social and cultural rights are based fundamentally on the concept of social equality (also called ‘freedom to’) are related to the 
guarantee of minimum necessities of the life to human beings. In the absence of these rights the existence of human beings is like to be endangered.

Right to adequate food, clothing, housing and adequate standard of living and freedom from hunger, right to work , right to social security, right to 
physical and mental health and right to education are included in this category of rights. These rights sometimes called positive rights require active
intervention, not abstentions on the part of the states. 
The enjoyment of these rights requires a major commitment of resources and therefore their realization cannot be immediate as in the case of civil 
and political rights.

Although the United Nations has recognized the above two sets of rights in two separate Covenants i.e. International covenant on civil and political 
rights ( ICCPR) and International covenant on economic social and cultural rights ( ICESCR) there is a close relationship between them. It has been 
rightly realized especially by the developing countries that civil and political rights can have no meaning unless they are accompanied by social,
economic and cultural rights. Thus both categories of rights are equally important and where civil and political rights do not exist, there cannot
be full realization of economic, social and cultural rights and vice versa.</text>
    </Information>
  </Types>
  
    
</Maininformation>